Guide to the Naum Gabo Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1920-1975; Series II; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  - Writings About Naum Gabo
    - Richman, Robert: Seascapes and Sea Music Endangered Phoenix (Box 44)
    - W.W. Wittenbert: "Reconstruction of Gabo" (Box 44)
    - Miriam Gabo: "Kay Sage Tanguey" (Box 44)
    - Herbert Read: "Naum Gabo. Introduction" (Box 44)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Gabo: Obituaries, 3 (Box 45)
    - Architectural Design, Bitenkorf (Box 45)
    - Architectural Record (Box 45)
    - Gene Bard: "The Gabo Retrospective" (Box 45)
    - Bauhaus (Box 45)
    - Aanf Behne: "Wie Stent der Proletarier zur Morernen Kunst" (Box 45)
    - Belgian TV (Box 45)
    - Bier, Justus, "Gabo" (Box 45)
    - Boustedt (Box 45)
    - Buffalo 1968 Exhibition- Catalogues - Plus by Minus: Today's Half Century (Box 45)
    - Chanin (Box 45)
    - Chermayeff (Box 45)
    - Clay (Box 45)
    - Egyseg (Box 45)
    - GSD Bulletin (Box 45)
    - P.B. Gheusi (Box 45)
    - Hess (Box 45)
    - Hinks (Box 45)
    - Hulten (Box 45)
    - Jordan (Box 45)
    - Kallai (Box 45)
    - Kepes (Box 45)
    - Konst-Och Musikhistoria (Box 45)
    - Konstrevy, 2 (Box 45)
    - Hilton Kramer: "Gabo and Constructivism: History Revised" (Box 45)
    - Hilton Kramer: "Small Avant-Garde in Soviet Art Departs from Official Socialist Realist Style" (Box 45)
    - Review of Gabo (Box 45)
    - London Gallery Invitation to Gabo Exhibition (Box 45)
    - De Mely (Box 45)
    - Cubism and Abstract Art MOMA 1936 Press Release (Box 46)
    - Mumford (Box 46)
    - National Review (Box 46)
    - Plastics (Box 46)
    - La Propriedad (Box 46)
    - A Century of Sculpture,Rhode Island School of Design (Box 46)
    - Richman, Robert and others (Box 46)
    - Rickey (Box 46)
    - Romare (Box 46)
    - Salmon (Box 46)
    - Sandberg (Box 46)
    - Schweicher: "Das Warenhaus 'Die Bitenkorf'" (Box 46)
    - J.J. Sweeney: "Construction Unconstructible?" (Box 46)
    - Signals (Box 46)
    - Seeley (Box 46)
    - J.T. Soby: "The Constructivist Brotherhood" (Box 46)
    - Sylvester (Box 46)
    - "Art: Exhibitions: Where the Animals Roam" (Box 46)
    - W. Trevor (Box 46)
    - Voskuil (Box 46)
    - E.W. (Box 46)
    - Wadsworth Atheneum (Box 46)
    - Whitford (Box 46)
    - S. John Woods and D. Lewis (Box 46)
    - Xagoraris, Panteilis (Box 46)
    - Comments on the work of Naum Gabo - by Ann Martino, 3 (Box 47)
  - Other Publications
    - Fragment of German Publications re: color and optics (Box 47)
    - Published Writings not about Gabo - "Houses and Ships Made Fireproof" (Box 47)
    - Periodical Writings not about Gabo - Architectural Record July 1951 - J. E. Burchard, "Humanity Our Client" (Box 47)
    - Aujourd'hui (Box 47)
    - Berliner Illustrierte Zeitune (Box 47)
    - Design Research Unit (Box 47)
    - H. Harine (Box 47)
    - Leaflet for International Arts Centre, London (Box 47)
    - Konstrevy, 2 (Box 47)
    - Publications not about Gabo - Krause, Hugo Rezepte Fur Die Werkstatt (Box 47)
    - Life (Box 47)
    - Published Writings by others not about Gabo - Lissitzky, Ed "Imaginarer Raum" (Box 47)
    - Listener, 3 (Box 47)
    - Listener, 3 (Box 48)
    - New Statesman (Box 48)
    - Louisiana Revy (Box 48)
    - Mumford, Lewis. New Yorker (Box 48)
    - N. Philips: "Festival Sculptress" John Bull 23 Sept., 1950 (Box 48)
    - L'Oeil (Box 48)
    - Pendulo (Box 48)
    - Rickey, George: "The New Tendency (Nouvelle Tendance - Recherche continuelle) Art Journal XXIII, 4, 1964 (Box 48)
    - Panderma No.3 November 1959 Hugo Ball (Box 48)
    - Saarinen: "San Paolo Report" (Box 48)
    - Saturday Evening Post (Box 48)
    - Saturday Review (Box 48)
    - Juri Semjonow: "Der Zweite Funfjahresplan Sowjetrusslands" (Box 48)
    - Spain Illustrated (Box 48)
    - Trend (Box 48)
    - Zeitschrift Des Vereines Deutscher Ingenierure (Box 48)
- Other Material, 1955-1977; Series III; 11.06; (28 boxes)
  Series III. Other Material contains all other material relating to Gabo in the collection, including constructions (models), drawings, photographs, audiovisual materials, financial and legal records, printed materials, and personal papers, such as passports and family records. Audiovisual materials include audio recordings of talks by Gabo and 8 and 16mm films of Gabo by Ilya Bolotowsky.
  - Gabo drawing (Box 49)
  - Plan for unidentified exhibition (Box 49)
  - Photos of and relating to Gabo's constructions (Box 49)
  - Drawings for an optical apparatus (Box 49)
  - Drawing and specifications (Box 49)
  - Drawing of Dream House (Box 49)
  - Album of Drawings by Elizabeth Richter (Box 49)
  - Photographs of Photomontages (Box 49)
  - Photographs of the tribute to Naum Gabo at the Tate Gallery (Box 49)
  - Images of atrocities (Box 49)
  - Photographs of works by other artists (Box 49)
  - Personal photographs of Gabo alone and with others (Box 49)
  - Personal photographs of Elizabeth Richter (Box 49)
  - Personal photographs of Aleksei Pevsner and family in USSR (Box 49)
  - Map of Moscow showing area for development in Gabo's Palace of Soviets' project (Box 49)
  - Photographs of concentrations camps (Box 49)
  - Newspaper cuttings concerning Spanish Civil War (Box 49)
  - Newspaper cuttings misc., 3 (Box 49)
  - Newspaper cuttings concerning Second World War (Box 49)
  - Clippings showing Gabo's influence (Box 49)
  - Postcards of art works (Box 49)
  - Postcards of various cities (Box 49)
  - German dress pattern (Box 49)
  - Redslob 1924 to police (Box 50)
  - List of Berlin addresses (Box 50)
  - Form concerning Gabo's carte d'identite (Box 50)
  - Gabo's Soviet passport (Box 50)
  - Gabo's carte d'identite (Box 50)
  - Certificate of Registration as Alien (Box 50)
  - British driving license (Box 50)
  - National Registration identity card, Great Britain (Box 50)
  - Address book (Box 50)
  - American passports, 6 (Box 50)
  - Gabo's will, 1976 (Box 50)
  - American passports for Miriam Gabo, 4 (Box 50)
  - American passport for Nina Gabo (Box 50)
  - Gabo diaries (datebooks), 1957-1959; 3 (Box 50)
  - Calendars, 1967-1977; 9 (Box 50)
  - Gabo's list of his gramophone records compiled by Miriam Gabo (Box 50)
  - Receipts (Box 51)
  - Dresden Bank (Box 51)
  - Household and financial (Box 51)
  - Aubry Bell Ltd. Decorators (Box 51)
  - Beachcraft and Co. (Box 51)
  - Removal from Cholmly Gardens to Cornwall Household - Faerystone Carbls Bay, 3 (Box 51)
  - Misc. receipts, unsorted, 5 (Box 51)
  - Notes on learning English and some cards (Box 51)
  - Mortgage for Woodbury House (Box 52)
  - Breakneck Hill House - Hirsh Brothers, 3 (Box 52)
  - Breakneck Hill - mortgage/bill of sale (Box 52)
  - Medical matters (Box 52)
  - Woodbury Savings Bank (Box 52)
  - Drucas and Attlee (Box 52)
  - Misc. unsorted receipts (Box 52)
  - Household - Burton Insurance (Box 53)
  - Connecticut Light (Box 53)
  - Middlebury - Carlson Decorators (Box 53)
  - Summer camps for Nina (Box 53)
  - Middlebury - Colonial Trust Co. (Box 53)
  - Woodbury - Carmody, Larkin and Torrence (Box 53)
  - American Fidelity Co. (Box 53)
  - Ileana (Box 53)
  - Misc. (Box 53)
  - Helene (Box 53)
  - Ex Libris Catalogues (Box 53)
  - Woodbury Mortgage (Box 53)
  - Correspondence A-Z (Box 53)
  - Miscellaneous notes and lists by Gabo + Mrs. Gabo (Box 53)
  - Unidentified (Box 53)
  - Bills, 1968-1969; 18 (Box 54)
  - Westminster Bank papers, 8 (Box 55)
  - Financial records, 1968; 4 (Box 56)
  - Financial records, 1969; 4 (Box 57)
  - 1970 tax papers (Box 58)
  - 1970 financial records, 4 (Box 59)
  - 1971 financial records, 4 (Box 60)
  - 1971 financial records, 4 (Box 61)
  - 1972 taxes and home, 4 (Box 62)
  - 1973 taxes and other, 4 (Box 63)
  - 1973 taxes and other, 4 (Box 64)
  - 1974 taxes, 4 (Box 65)
  - 1974 (not taxes), 4 (Box 66)
  - 1975 financial records, 4 (Box 67)
  - 1976 financial records, 4 (Box 68)
  - 1977 taxes, 4 (Box 69)
  - 1977 taxes and non-taxes, 4 (Box 70)
  - Printed material (Box 71)
  - Printed material (Box 72)
  - Audiovisual material, 7 (Box 73)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 73 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Gabo, Christian Science Monitor, 1968 February; 1; 01:24:46 (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360845)
    - Naum Gabo reading "Manifesto", London, 1967 November; 1; 00:17:24 (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360852)
      7.5 ips; full track
    - Gabo, Starr-Frampton, 1969 March 20; 1; 02:01:58; A high amount of hum can be heard on this audiotape reel. The program is distorted at times. (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360860)
    - Gabo, Lines Cha[p]es, Volumes, Space and other nonsense, 1952 April 14, 15 and 17; 1; 02:02:47; This program was recorded at a very low level. (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360878)
    - Naum Gabo talk, Fest #4, 1968 March 3; 1; 00:37:43 (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360886)
    - Naum Gabo talk, Fest #4, 1968 March 3; 1; 00:37:44; Static can be heard on this audiotape reel. The program is distorted at times. (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360894)
    - Gen conversation + beginning of unknown English architect teacher..., undated; 1; 01:08:10; Drastic speed fluctuations can be heard on this audiotape reel. The first 31 minutes of the program was recorded at a very low level. A high amount of hum can be heard on the recording. The program is distorted at times. (Box 73, Item barcode 39002099360902)
      Contents include: Gabo reciting poems
  - Film, 4 (Box 74)
    Contains 8 and 16mm film reels.
    Box 74 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Envelope relating to film canisters (Box 75)
  - Film by Ilya Bolotowsky, 1955 December 12, Swedish TV Film, undated; YCALMSS541_0001; 1; 00:14:59 (Box 75, Item barcode 39002102338358)
    Box 75 (video tape): Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Photographs, Greece, 1971 (Box 75)
  - Objects (Box 76 art)
- Material Relating to Antoine Pevsner, undated; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series IV. contains material relating to Naum Gabo's older brother Antoine Pevsner.
  - Declaration (Box 77)
  - Photographs of Pevsner (Box 77)
  - Photographs showing Pevsner's works installed at 1948 MOMA Exhibition, 3 (Box 77)
  - Newspaper cuttings about Pevsner (Box 77)
  - Aujourd'hui, 2 (Box 77)
  - Pierre Gueguen "Pevsner et al conquete plastique de l'espace" (Box 77)
  - Massat re: Pevsner (Box 77)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  - Dictaphone belt (In Series II) (Box 78)